本节我们看Diffie-Hellman协议
In this segment, we're gonna look at the
Diffie-Hellman protocol, which is our
这是我们的第一个实用的密钥交换机制。
那么让我为大家讲一下目前的设定。
first practical key exchange mechanism. So
let me remind you of the settings. Our
我们的朋友Alice和Bob素未谋面，却想交换一个共享密钥
friends here, Alice and Bob, have never
met and yet they wanna exchange a shared
然后他们可以使用这个密钥来用于相互安全通信
secret key that they can then use to
communicate securely with one another.
这两节我们只看对窃听攻击的安全性
In this segment and the next, we're only
gonna be looking at eavesdropping
换句话说，我们只关心窃听攻击者
security. In other words, we only care
about eavesdroppers. The attackers are
攻击者不能篡改网络中的数据
actually not allowed to tamper with data
in the network. They're not allowed to
他们不能修改数据包，不能以任何方式改数据包
inject packets. They're not allowed to
change packets in any way. All they do is
他们只能窃听网络流量。在密钥交换协议的最后
to just eavesdrop on the traffic. And at
the end of the protocol, the key exchange
我们的朋友Alice和Bob应该有一个共享密钥
protocol our friends Alice and Bob should
have a shared secret key but the attacker
但窃听攻击者无法知道交换的密钥是什么
namely the eavesdropper has no idea what
that key's gonna be. In the previous
上一节我们看了所谓的Merkle谜题的协议
segment we looked at a key segment called
Merkle puzzles. That's just using block
只使用分组密码和哈希函数。我还告诉大家
ciphers or hash functions. And I showed
you that there that basically the attacker
攻击者有一个平方鸿沟，相比于参与者。换句话说
has a quadratic gap compared to the
participants. In other words if the
如果参与者花了与N成正比的时间，那么攻击者
participants spent time proportional to N
the attacker can break the protocol in
能在与N平方成正比的时间里破解这个协议。
因此这个协议从应用角度来看是不安全的
time proportional to N squared. And as a
result that protocol is too insecure to be
本节我们研究，我们能否做同样的事情
considered practical. In this segment we
are going to ask whether we can do the
但现在能获得一个指数级鸿沟，横亘在
same thing but now we'd like to achieve an
exponential gap between the attacker's
攻击者和参与者的工作之间。换句话说，Alice和Bob
work ended up in the participant's work.
In other words, Alice and Bob might do
可以做与N成正比的工作，但为了破解这个协议
work proportional to N, but to break the
protocol the attacker is gonna have to do
攻击者必须做与N的某个指数级成正比的工作量
work proportional to some exponential in
N. So now there's an exponential gap
现在，在参与者和攻击者的工作之间
有一条指数级鸿沟。那么如我上节所说
between the participants work and the
attacker's work. So as I said in the
我们不能获得这个指数级鸿沟，仅凭
previous segment we can't achieve this
exponential gap from block ciphers like AES
想AES或SHA-256这样的分组密码技术。我们必须
使用拥有比对称原型更多结构的难解问题
or SHA-256. We have to use hard problems
that have more structure than just those
那么我们使用一点代数
symmetric primitives. And so instead what
we're gonna do is use a little bit of algebra.
本节我将描述Diffie-Hellman协议
In this segment I'm gonna
describe the Diffie-Hellman protocol very
以很具体的形式，不是很形式化。
下周我们还会回到Diffie-Hellman协议
concretely and somewhat informally. When
we're gonna come back to Diffie-Hellman next week
我们将更为抽象地描述这个协议
and we're gonna describe the protocol more
abstractly and we're gonna do a much more
我们将对这个协议进行更为严格的安全性分析。
那么Diffie-Hellman协议是如何工作的呢？
rigorous security analysis of this
protocol. Okay, so how does Diffie-Hellman
首先，我们选某个固定的大质数
work? What we're gonna do is, first of
all, we're gonna fix some large prime
记之为p。我通常用p表示质数
which I'm gonna call p. Actually p I'll
usually use to denote primes. And you
大家应该把它想象成非常大的质数。比如
should be thinking of really gigantic
primes. Like, primes that are made up of
有600个十进制位的质数。如果大家喜欢用二进制的话
600 digits are so. And just for those of
you who like to think in binary, a 600
600个十进制位大约相当于2000个二进制位
digit prime roughly corresponds to about
2000 bits. So just writing down the prime
写下了约两千位的质数。然后我们选一个
固定的整数g
takes about two kilo bits of data. And
then we're also gonna fix an integer g
g正好在从1到p的范围中。这里的p和g
that happens to live in the range one to
p. So these values p and g are parameters
是Diffie-Hellman协议的参数。它们一经选择就不再改变
of the Diffie-Hellman protocol. They are
chosen once and they're fixed forever. Now
现在这个协议如下工作。这是我们的朋友Alice和Bob
the protocol works as follow. So here's
our friends Alice and Bob. So what Alice's
开始时Alice选择某个随机数a，范围是1到p-1
going to do is she's gonna starts off by
choosing some random number a in the range 1 to p-1
然后她将计算g^a mod p
And then she is gonna compute
the number g to the power of a modulo p.
她计算这个指数，然后将结果取质数p的模
Okay, so she computes this exponention,
and reduces the result modular the prime p.
下一章中我们将看到如何有效地计算这个有限域上的指数
And we're actually going to see how to
compute this efficiently the next module,
现在请大家姑且相信我，这是可以有效计算的
so for now just believe me that this
computation can be done efficiently.
现在，我们记A为这个计算的结果
Now, let's call capital A the result of this
value. So, what Alice will do is she will
那么Alice会把A发送给Bob。现在Bob做同样的事情
send capital A over to Bob. Now Bob is
going to do the same thing. He's going to
他选择一个随机数b，范围从1到p-1
choose a random number b in the range 1
to p-1. He's going to compute g to
Bob计算g^b mod p，我们记结果为B
the b module of p and let's call this
number B and he's going to send this
然后Bob把B发送给Alice。那么Alice发送了A给Bob，
Bob发送了B给Alice
number B over to Alice. So Alice sends A
to Bob. Bob sends B To Alice. And now
现在他们俩宣布，他们已经共享了一个密钥。
那么这个共享的密钥是什么呢？
they claim that they can generate a shared
secret key. So what's a shared secret key?
我们来定义它，我们先记之为K_AB
Well, it's defined as. Let's call it
K_AB. And it's basically defined as the
K_AB定义为g^ab mod p。现在Diffie-Hellman在
1976年的一个惊人的观察结果是
value g to the power of a times b. Now the
amazing observation of Diffie-Hellman had
事实上双方都可以计算这个值g^ab mod p
back in 1976 is that in fact both parties
can compute this value g to the ab.
我们看，Alice可以计算这个值，因为她可以取值B
So let's see, Alice can compute this value
because she can take her value B that she
B是Bob给她的。她可以取值B，计算B^a mod p
received from Bob. She can take this value
B, raise it to the power of a and, let's
她会获得g^ab mod p
see, what she'll get is g to the b to the
power of b. And by the rules of
根据指数规则，(g^b)^a=(g^a)^b mod p
exponentiation, g to the power of b to the
power of a is equal to g to the ab. Bob
Bob实际上也可以做类似的事情，那么
他的目标是计算(g^a)^b mod p
turns out, can do something similar, so
his goal is to compute g to the a to the b,
答案依然是g^ab mod p，所以Alice和Bob
都可以计算出K_AB
which again, is g to the ab, so both
Alice and Bob will have computed K_AB, and
我问大家，Bob是怎么计算g^ab mod p的？
let me ask you, how does Bob actually
compute this quantity g to the ab?
他取Alice给他的A
Well so all he does is he takes the value A that
he received from Alice and he raises it to
计算A^b mod p，就得到了共享密钥g^ab mod p
his own secret b and that gives him the
shared secret g to the ab. So you can see
大家可以看到，尽管双方计算的值不一样
now that both parties even though they
seemingly computed different values. In
事实上他们会得到同样的值g^ab mod p
fact they both end up with the same value
namely g ab module p. I should mention by
我应该顺便提到，Martin Hellman和Whit Diffie
于1976年提出这一协议
the way that Martin Hellman and Wig
Diffie came up with this protocol back in
当时Martin Hellman是斯坦福的教授，
而Whit Diffie是他的研究生
1976. Martin Hellman was a professor here
at Stanford and Wig Diffie was his
他们提出的这个协议真正改变了这个世界
graduate student. They came up with this
protocol and this protocol really changed
它开创了密码学的新纪元
the world. In that it introduced this new
age in cryptography. Where now it's not just
现在不仅仅是关于开发分组密码，而且是关于
about developing block ciphers but it's
actually about designing algebraic
设计基于代数的协议，使之拥有类似我们这里的性质
protocols that have properties like the
one we see here. So you notice that what
大家注意，这个协议顺利工作的本质原因
是指数的代数性质
makes this protocol works is basically
properties of exponentiation. Namely that,
即(g^b)^a = (g^a)^b
g to the b to the power of a is the same
as g to the a to the power of b, okay?
这些是指数的性质。现在当我描述
These are just properties of
exponentiations. Now when I describe a
一个像我刚才展示给大家的协议时，
大家应该想到的真正问题
protocol like the one I just showed you.
The real question that should be in your
不是这个协议为什么能工作。换句话说，
很容易验证这点
mind is not why the protocol works. In
other words, it's very easy to verify
事实上，Alice和Bob最后会得到同样的密钥
that, in fact, both Alice and Bob end up
with the same secret key. The bigger
更重要的问题是，为什么这个协议是安全的？
换句话说，为什么一个窃听者
question is why is this protocol secure?
In other words, why is it that an
无法根据双方发出的A、B，解出共享密钥？
eavesdropper cannot figure out the same
shared key due to the AB that both Alice
让我们稍作分析，如我所说
and Bob computed by themselves? So let's
analyze this a little bit, then, like I
下周我们进行更进一步的分析
said, we're gonna do a much more in-depth
analysis next week. But, let's, for now,
现在我们先直观地看一下问什么这个协议是安全的
just see intuitively why this protocol is
gonna be secure. Well, what does the
窃听者能看到什么？他能看到质数和生成元
eavesdropper see? Well, he sees the prime
and the generator. These are just fixed
(这里质数是指上文的p，生成元是指g)
这些值是永远固定不变的，每个人都知道它们。
攻击者还能看到Alice发给Bob的值A
forever and everybody knows who they are.
He also sees the value that Alice sent to
他还能看到Bob发给Alice的值B
Bob, namely this capital A. And he sees
the value that Bob sent to Alice, namely
问题是，窃听者能计算出g^ab mod p
this capital B. And the question is, can
the, can the eavesdropper compute g to the
仅根据这四个值吗？更一般地
ab just given these four values? So more
generally, what we can do is we can define
我们可以定义这个Diffie-Hellman函数。
我们说，Diffie-Hellman函数
this Diffie-Hellman function. So we'll say
that the Diffie-Hellman function is defined
定义在某个值g上，问题是，给定g^a和g^b
based on some value g. And the question is
given g to the a, and g to the b. Can you
能否计算g^ab？我们在问，计算这个
compute g to the ab? And what we're
asking is how hard is it to compute this
很大的质数模p乘法群上的函数，有多困难？
记得p大约有600个十进制位
function module over very large prime p.
Remember p was something like 600 digits.
所以真正的问题是，这个Diffie-Hellman函数
So the real question we need to answer is
how hard is this, is this Diffie-Hellman
有多难解？我来告诉大家目前已知的事实。
介绍这个质数正好有n位长
function? So let me show you what's known
about this. So suppose the prime happens
在我们这里比如说n=2000位
to be n bits long. Okay, so in our case
say n is 2,000 bits. It turns out the best
实际上计算Diffie-Hellman函数，已知最好的算法
known algorithm for computing the
DiffieCHellman function. Is actually a
是一个更为一般的算法，用来计算离散对数函数
more general algorithm that computes the
discrete log function, which we're gonna
我们下周讨论它。但现在，我们就说这个算法
talk about next week. But for now, let's
just say that this algorithm computes a
能计算Diffie-Hellman函数。这个算法叫做
普通数域筛法
Diffie-Hellman function. The algorithm is
called a general number field sieve. I'm
我这里不描述它是如何工作的，不过如果大家
想听一听它是如何工作的
not gonna describe how it works, although
if you'd want to hear how it works, let me
告诉我们，我们会在课程的最后开一个特殊专题
know, and that could be one of the special
topics that we cover at the end of the
有趣的是，这个算法的运行时间是指数级的
course. But the interesting thing is that
its running time is exponential in
指数大约是n的立方根。换句话说，运行时间
roughly the cube root of n. In other
words, the running time is roughly e to
大约是e的n的立方根次方。事实上这个算法的
运行时间的严格表达式
the power of o of cube root of n. So in
fact the exact expression for the running
要比这个复杂得多
time, of this algorithm is much more
complicated than this. I'm deliberately
我故意简化了，以求直击要点
simplifying it here just to kind of get
the point across. The point that I want to
我想强调的一点是，事实上，这不是严格的指数时间的算法
emphasize is that in fact, this is not
quite an exponential time algorithm.
指数时间是指e^n。这个算法有时叫做亚指数算法
Exponential would be e to the power of n.
This is sometimes called a sub-exponential
因为这里的指数项正比于n的立方根
algorithm because the exponent is really
just proportional to the cube root of n,
而不是n。这说明即使这个问题很难
as opposed to linear n. What this says is
that even though this problem is quite
他也不是真正的指数级时间的问题
difficult, it's not really an exponential
time problem. The running time in the
运行时间的指数是与n的立方根成正比的
exponent is gonna be just proportional to
the cube root of n. So let's look at some
那么我们来看几个例子。假设我正好在看一个模
examples. Suppose I happen to be looking
at a modulus that happens to be about a
有大于一千位长。这个算法是说
thousand bits long. What this algorithm
says is that we can solve the
我们可以解决Diffie-Hellman问题，以时间
大约是e的1024的立方根次方
Diffie-Hellman problem in time that's
approximately e to the cube root of 1,024.
这不是很准确，事实上指数上有一些常数项
Now this is not really correct, in fact
there are more constants in the exponent.
但只看要点的话，我们可以说算法的运行时间
But again, just to get, the point across,
we can say that the running time would be
大约是e的1024的立方根次方，这个值其实很小，
大约是e的10次方(约22000)
roughly e to the cube root of 1,024; which
is actually very small, roughly e to the 10.
这个简单的例子告诉大家，如果你有一个亚指数级算法
So the simple example shows you that
if you have a sub-exponential algorithm,
大家看到即使这个问题规模很大，比如1000位
you see that even if the problem is quite
large, like 1,000 bits. Because of the
因为这个立方根的作用，其实总体并没有那么大
cube root effect the exponent actually is not
that big overall. Now to be honest I'm
说实话我就讲到这里了。普通数域筛法
actually lying here. General number field
sieve actually have many other
在指数上有许多其他常数，不如事实上
这个根本不是10
constants in the exponents so in fact this
is not going to be ten at all. It's
而是类似于80的样子。因为指数上的各种常数
actually going to be something like 80.
Because of various constants in the
但是大家看到这个问题依然比2的1000次方
exponents. But nevertheless but you see
the problem is much harder than say 2 to
(这里讲反了。筛法降低了问题复杂性)
困难得多。尽管描述它需要1000位，但解决它
the 1000. Even though describing it takes
1,000 bits, solving it does not take time
不需要1000次方的时间。这里我把表往下拉
to the 1,000. So here I roll down the
table that kind of shows you the rough
给大家看大体上，比较一下破解Diffie-Hellman协议
difficulty of breaking down the
Diffie-Hellman protocol compared to the
和破解分组密码的难度，给定合适的位数。例如
difficulty of breaking down a cipher with
a appropriate number of bits. For example,
如果你的密码有80位密钥，那大概需要1000位的模
if your cipher has 80 bit keys. That would
be roughly comparable to using 1,000 bit
换句话说，破解一个80位的密码，大约需要2的80次方的时间
modules. In other words breaking a cipher
with 80 bit keys takes time roughly 2 to the 80
意味着如果你的Diffie-Hellman函数有1000位的模
which means that breaking if you have Diffie-Hellman function with a 1,000
破解它需要2的80次方的时间
bit module will take time 2 to the 80.
如果你的密码使用128位密钥，比如AES，那么
你应该使用3000位的模
If your cipher uses 128 bit keys like AES, you should be
really using a 3,000 bit modulus,
即使没有人真正这样做。实际中，人们使用2000位的模
even though nobody really does this. In reality
people would use 2,000 bit modulus. And
那么如果你的密钥非常大，比如说如果
我们使用256位AES密钥
then if your key is very large, like if
we're using a 256 bit AES key, then in
那么事实上你的模需要非常大。大家可以看到
fact your modulus needs to be very, very
large. Again, you, you can really see the
这里立方根的作用了。由于这个立方根的影响，
我们将密钥大小翻倍时
cube root effect here. We doubled the size
of our key and because of the cube root
意味着我们必须增加模的大小，倍数为
effect, what that means is we have to
increase the size of, of our modulus by a
2的立方，也就是8倍，这就是这个15000的由来
factor of two cubed, namely a factor of
eight, which is where this 15,000 comes from.
我应该再提一下，这并不是严格的8倍
from. And again I should mention there's
not exactly a factor of eight because of
因为指数上有其他常数项。那么这张表不错
the extra constants in the exponent. So
this is a nice table that shows you that
它告诉大家，如果大家要使用Diffie-Hellman协议
来交换会话密钥
if you're gonna be using Diffie-Hellman to
exchange, a session key. And that session
用于分组密码的会话密钥要有合适的密钥大小
key is gonna be used for a block cipher
with a certain key size, this table shows
这张表为大家展示了，需要使用的模大小，
使得密钥交换协议的安全性
you what modular size you need to use so
that the security of the key exchange
和你之后使用的分组密码的安全性相当
protocol is comparable to the security of
the block cipher you're gonna be using after.
现在这个最后一行应该会困扰着大家
Now this last row should
really be disturbing to you. I should tell
我应该告诉大家，要使用如此之大的模很成问题
you that working with such a large modulus
is very problematic. This is actually
速度会很慢，那么问题是，我们能否做得更好？
gonna be quite slow, and so the question
is whether there is anything better that
实际上是有的。事实上，我描述Diffie-Hellman函数的方法
we can do? And it turns out there is. In
fact the way I describe the Diffie-Hellman
正是Diffie和Hellman在1976年描述的方法
function is I describe it at the way
Diffie and Hellman described it in 1976
使用了质数模的算术。质数模算术的问题是
using arithmetic module of primes. The
problem with arithmetic modular primes is
Diffie-Hellman函数难以计算，但不如大家想的那么难
that the Diffie-Hellman function is hard
to compute, but it's not as hard as you'd
有这个立方根的影响，使之比大家想的稍容易些
like. There's this cube root effect that
makes it a little easier than what you'd
那么问题是，我们能否在其他的设定下，
运行Diffie-Hellman协议
really like. And so the question is can we
run the Diffie-Hellman protocol in other
实际上答案是肯定的。事实上我们可以
settings. And it turns out the answer is
yes. In fact we can literally translate
把Diffie-Hellman协议从质数模算术的设定
the Diffie-Hellman protocol from an
arithmetic model of primes to a different
翻译成不同类型的代数对象，然后在其他的
type of algebraic object and solving the
Diffie-Hellman problem on that other
代数对象上解Diffie-Hellman问题将是困难得多。
这个其他的代数对象就是
algebraic object is much, much harder.
This other algebraic object is what's
所谓的椭圆曲线。如我所说，计算定义在椭圆曲线域上的
Diffie-Hellman函数
called an elliptic curve. And as I said,
computing the Diffie-Hellman function on
要比计算质数模乘法群上的Diffie-Hellman困难得多
these elliptic curves is much harder than
computing the Diffie-Hellman modulo primes.
因为问题更加困难，现在我们可以使用小得多的代数对象
Because the problem is so much harder, now
we can use much smaller objects in
特别地，我们使用仅有160位或80位或
particular, you know we'd be using primes
that are only a 160 bits or 80 bit keys or
512位的质数，用于256位的分组密钥。那么因为这些模
only 512 bits for 256 bit keys. So because
these module don't grow as
在椭圆曲线上增长得不快，通常从使用模算术
fast on elliptic curves, there's generally
a slow transition away from using module
到使用椭圆曲线有一个缓慢的转换。
我这里先不为大家描述椭圆曲线
arithmetic, to using elliptic curves. I'm
not going to describe elliptic curves
但如果这是大家想学习的
right now for you, but if this is
something you'd like to learn about I can
我可以留到本课程的最后一周，届时讨论更多高级话题
do that at the very last week of the
course, when we discuss more advanced
(实际上在第二季，敬请期待)
但事实上当我们下周回到Diffie-Hellman时
topics. But in fact when we come back to
Diffie-Hellman next week I'm gonna describe it
我将更为抽象地描述它，这样你使用的代数结构就不重要了
more abstractly so that it really doesn't
matter which algebraic structure you use
无论使用质数模算术，还是使用椭圆曲线域
whether you use arithmetic model of primes
or whether you use a elliptic curve we
我们都可以将整个过程抽象出来，然后使用
这个Diffie-Hellman概念
can kinda abstract that whole issue away
and then use the Diffie-Hellman concept a for
进行密钥交换，以及一些其他事情。如我所说
key exchange and for other things as well.
And as I said we'll see that more
我们下周还会看到更多的抽象。通常我想展示这个漂亮的协议
abstractly next week. So as usual I wanna
show that this beautiful protocol that I
就像我刚刚展示给大家的，Diffie-Hellman协议，
对抗主动攻击时，是完全不安全的
just showed you, the Diffie-Hellman protocol,
is as is, is actually completely insecure
它是完全不安全的
against an active attack. Namely, it's
completely insecure against what's called
当存在所谓的中间人攻击。我们需要对这个协议
the man in the middle attack. We need to
do something more than this protocol to
做些补充，让它对中间人攻击也是安全的。
下周，我们将再次回到Diffie-Hellman协议
make is secure against man in the middle.
And again we're gonna come back to Diffie
让它能安全地抵抗中间人攻击。好，那现在我们看
Hellman and make it secure against man in
the middle next week. Okay. So let's see
为什么我刚才展示给大家的这个协议
对主动攻击是不安全的
why the protocol that I just showed you is
insecure against active attacks. Well
假设我们有这个中间人，他试图窃听
suppose we have this man in the middle
that's trying to eavesdrop on the
Alice和Bob之间的会话。协议开始时
conversation between Alice and Bob. Well
so, the protocol starts with Alice sending
Alice发送g^a给Bob。那么中间人截获了这个g^a
g to the a over to Bob. Well, so the man
in the middle is gonna intercept that and
他将取Alice发出的信息，换成他自己的信息
he's gonna take the message that Alice
sent and he's gonna replace it with his
我们记为A'，写成g^a'
own message. So it's called A', And
let's write that is g to the a'.
所以中间人选择了他自己的a'
Okay? So the man in the middle chooses his
own a' and what he sends to Bob is
把g^a'发送给Bob。现在可怜的Bob并不知道
actually g to the a'. Now poor Bob
doesn't know that the man in the middle
中间人对通信流量做了手脚，他只能获得值A'
actually did anything to this traffic, all
he sees is he got the value A'. As
他目前只知道，这个值来自Alice，那他怎么回复？
far as he knows, that value came from
Alice. So what is he gonna do in response?
Bob会回复他的值B=g^b给Alice
Well, he's gonna send back his value B out
which is g to the b back to Alice. Well
中间人截获了这个B
again the man in the middle is gonna
intercept this B. He's gonna generate his
他将产生自己的b'，然后发送B'=g^b'给Alice
own b' and what he actually sends
back to Alice is B' which is g to the b'.
现在会发生什么？Alice将计算她的密钥
Okay, now what happens? Well
Alice is gonna compute her part of the
她得到g^ab'。Bob也会计算他的密钥
secret key and she's gonna get g to the ab'. Bob is gonna compute his part of
他会得到g^ba'
the secret key and he's gonna get g to the
b times a'. Okay, these now you
现在大家注意到这些不是一样的密钥。而对于中间人
notice these are not the same keys. In the
man in the middle because he knows both A'
他既知道A'又知道B'，他既可以计算g^ab'
也可以计算g^ba'
and B' he can compute both g to
the ab' and g to ba'. Yeah it's
不难看出中间人同时知道两个值。因此
not difficult to see the man in the middle
knows both values. And as a result, now he
现在他可以扮演中间人，当Alice发送一个加密的信息
can basically play this man in the middle
and when Alice sends an encrypted message
给Bob，中间人可以轻松解密这个信息
to Bob the man in the middle can simply
decrypt this message because he knows the
因为他知道Alice加密信息的密钥。然后中间人
重新使用Bob的密钥加密这个信息
secret key that Alice encrypted message
with, re-encrypt it using Bob's key. And
然后把信息发送给Bob。这样Alice发送信息给Bob
then send the message on over to Bob. And
this way Alice sent the message, Bob
Bob接收信息。Bob认为这个信息是安全的
received the message. Bob thinks the
message is secure. But in fact that
但事实上这个信息经过了中间人。中间人解密信息
message went through the man in the
middle. The man in the middle decrypted
然后为Bob重新加密了它。同时他可以完全读到信息内容
it, re-encrypted it for Bob. At the same
time he was able to completely read it,
如果他愿意，他可以修改它，等等。
所以这个协议是完全不安全的
modify it if he wants to, and so on. So,
the protocol becomes completely insecure
如果有中间人。所以如我所说，我们必须增强
give an man in the middle. And so as I
said we're gonna have to enhance the
这个协议以抵抗中间人攻击
protocol somehow to defend against men in
the middle but it turns out that it's
实际上增强和防御中间人攻击并不是很难
actually not that difficult to enhance and
prevent man in the middle attacks.
我们这两周内还将回来看。最后我想做的是
And we're gonna come back to that and see that
in a week or two. The last think I want to
为大家展示一个有趣的Diffie-Hellman协议的性质
do is show you an interesting property of
the Diffie-Hellman protocol. In fact, I
事实上我想给大家展示，这个协议可以被视为
一个非互动的协议
want to show you that this protocol can be
viewed as a non-interactive protocol. So,
我这话什么意思？设想我们有一组用户
what do I mean by that? So Imagine we have
a whole bunch of users, you know, millions
几百万用户。我们叫他们Alice, Bob, Charlie, David等等
of users. Let's call them Alice, Bob,
Charlie, David and so on and so forth.
他们中每个都将选取一个随机的私密值
Each one of them is going to choose a
random, secret value, and then on their
然后在他们的Facebook页面上，写下他们
Facebook profiles, they're gonna write
down, their contribution to the
对Diffie-Hellman协议的贡献。那么每个人写下了
Diffie-Hellman protocol. Alright so
everybody just writes down you know g to
g^a, g^b, g^c...现在，有趣的是
the a, g to the b, g to the c and so on.
Now the interesting thing about this is,
如果Alice和Charlie想建立一个共享密钥，他们无需相互通信
if say Alice and Charlie wanna set up a
shared key they don't need to communicate
Alice只要去Charlie的公共页面
at all. Basically Alice would go and read
Charlie's public profile. Charlie would go
Charlie只要去Alice的公共页面。刹那间，
他们就共享了一个密钥
and read Alice's public profile. And now,
boom, they immediately have a secret key.
Alice知道了g^ca。Charlie知道了g^ac
Namely, now, Alice knows, g to the c and
a. Charlie knows g to the a and с. And as
因此双方都能计算g^ac。某种意义上
a result, both of them can compute g to
the ac. So, in some sense, once they've
一旦他们在公共页面发布了他们对Diffie-Hellman协议的共享
posted their contributions to the
Diffie-Hellman protocol to their public
他们就根本不需要互相通信，就能建立共享密钥
profiles, they don't need to communicate
with each other at all to set up a shared key.
他们立即就能有一个共享密钥，现在他们
They immediately have a shared key
and now they can start communicating
就通过Facebook来安全地通信了，而不会是和别人
securely through Facebook or not with one
another. And notice that this is true for
注意这对所有Facebook用户都可以。只要我
去读某人的公共页面
any Facebook user. So as soon as I read
somebody's public profile, I immediately
我就能迅速得到一个共享密钥，无需互相通信
have a shared key with them without ever
communicating with them. This property is
这个性质有时叫做Diffie-Hellman的非互动性
sometimes called a non-interactive
property of the Diffie-Hellman. So now, let
让我给大家展示一个开放问题。这是一个开放问题
me show you an open problem. And this is
an open problem that's been open for ages
各个时代皆如此。如果大家有人能解决它，将是很好的
and ages and ages. So it'd be really cool
if one of you can actually solve it. The
问题是，我们能否对多于两方的用户做这些呢？换句话说
question is, can we do this for more than
two parties? In other words, say we have
比如说我们有四方。所有人都在他们的Facebook
公共页面上发布了他们的值
four parties. All of them post their
values to their Facebook profiles. And now
现在我们想只通过阅读Facebook页面
we'd like to make it that just by reading
Facebook profiles, all of them can set up
所有人都可以建立共享密钥。换句话说
a shared secret key. In other words, Alice
is, what she'll, she'll do is she'll only
Alice会去读其他三个朋友
Bob, Charlie和David的公共页面
read the public profiles of, the three
friends, Bob, Charlie and David. And
她已经可以计算和他们之间的共享密钥。
类似地，David只需
already she can compute a shared key with
them. And similarly David is just gonna
读Charlie的公共页面。Bob和Alice
read the public profile of Charlie. Bob
and Alice. And already he has a shared key
他就有了他们4个的共享密钥。问题是，
我们是否可以非互动地建立
with all four of them. Okay, so the
question is whether we can kind of setup
这些共享密钥，对多于两个人的组来说
non-interactively these, these shared keys
for groups that are larger than just two
如我所说，n=2就是Diffie-Hellman协议
people. So as I said, for n equals two,
this is just a Diffie-Hellman protocol. In
换句话说，如果只有双方想建立共享密钥
other words, if just two parties want to
set up a shared key without communicating
且无需相互通信，那么使用Diffie-Hellman即可
with one another, that's just
Diffie-Hellman. It turns out, for N equals
实际上对N=3的情况，我们也知道怎么做，
有一个已知的协议
three, we also know how to do it, there's
a known protocol, it's called protocol due
是由Joux提出的，它使用了非常高级的数学
to Joux. It already uses very, very fancy
mathematics, much more complicated
(Weil配对：e(B,C)^a=e(A,C)^b=e(A,B)^c=e(P,P)^abc)
比我刚刚为大家展示的要复杂得多的数学。
对于N=4或5或任何更大的数
mathematics than what I just showed you.
And for N equals four, or five, or
大于4的，这个问题是完全开放的
anything above this, above four, this
problem is completely open. Nearly the
这个情况下，4人在他们的公共页面上发布信息
case where four people post something to
the public profiles and then everybody
这样其他人读这些公共页面，然后他们
就有了一个公有的共享密钥
else reads the public profile and then
they have a joint shared key, this is
即使只有4人，我们也不知道怎么做
something we don't know how to do even for
four people. And this is a problem that's
这在各个时代都是一个开放的问题，是个有趣的问题
been open for ages and ages, it's kind of
a fun problem to think about and so see if
值得想一想，如果你能解决它，就会立即在密码学界有名气
you can solve it, if you will, it's
instant fame in the crypto world. Okay, so
我先说这么多，下节我们会继续讲另一个密钥交换机制
I'll stop here, and we'll continue with
another key exchange mechanism in the next segment.